Finding Aid for First Christian Church, Lansing, Mich., Records, 1890-1978
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
First Christian Church, Lansing, Mich., Records 1890-1978
First Christian Church (Lansing, Mich.)
4.5 linear ft. and 2 microfilm rolls
86773 Ba 2; Ba microcopy
First Christian Church (Disciples of Christ) of Lansing, Michigan. Records include newsletters, bulletins, yearbooks, board minutes, Ladies Aid Society records, correspondence and general files, and related materials; also photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was deposited by the church (donor no. 6347 ).
The record group is open to research.
The church was known in its early years (1912-1920) as the Capital Christian Church and later (1920-1957) as the First Church of Christ. In 1957 the congregation took its present name, First Christian Church.
The record group includes church board minutes; files of correspondence, memos and legal and financial papers; Sunday School attendance and offering record books; Bible (Sunday) School Council minutes and related materials; some individual Sunday School class record books; Vacation Bible School records; Ladies Aid Society minutes; Missions Committee minutes, correspondence and other materials; church yearbooks; church newsletters; worship service bulletins; photographs of church buildings and members; and miscellaneous materials having to do with the history of the congregation, its clergy and membership. The "Early Church Records" series is a microfilm copy of originals that remain at the church.
Subjects:
Charities--Michigan--Lansing.; Christian Church (Disciples of Christ)--Michigan--Lansing.; First Christian Church (Lansing, Mich.); Lansing (Mich.); Women--Michigan--Lansing--Societies and clubs.; Women--Religious life--Michigan--Lansing.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Churches--Michigan--Lansing.; Christian Church (Disciples of Christ)--Michigan--Lansing.; First Christian Church (Lansing, Mich.); Church buildings--Michigan--Lansing
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Church newsletters, bulletins, and other publications
  - The Church Messenger, 1947-1958 (Box 1)
  - First Christian News, 1958-ca. 1978 (Box 1)
  - Sunday worship service bulletins, 1952, 1954, 1963-ca. 1978 (Box 2)
  - Church yearbooks, 1939-1940, 1940-1942, 1954-1973 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous programs, including those for ordination and dedication services (Box 3)
- Financial and administrative
  - Church financial and legal records, 1890-1962, 5 folders (Box 3)
  - Church financial records, including bills for construction and furnishing of the new church building, 1927-1928 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous papers, 1960s-1970s and undated (Box 3)
- Church board minutes
  - 1950-1979, 29 folders (Box 4)
- Church groups
  - Ladies Aid Society records
    - 1914 (Box 4)
    - 1914-1918 (Box 4)
    - 1918-1919 (Box 4)
  - Women's Society records, 1937-1938 (Box 4)
  - Missions committee minutes, 1952-1957 (Box 4)
  - Missions committee correspondence and other records, 1951-1957 (Box 4)
- Sunday School
  - Attendance and offering records, 1949-1960, 12 folders (Box 4)
  - Bible school council minutes and other materials, 1955-1959 (Box 4)
  - Individual Sunday school class records
    - "Loyal Berean" class, 1920-1922 (Box 4)
    - "Kum Join Us" class, 1940-1942 (Box 4)
    - "Lookout" class, 1947-1955, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - "Builders" class, 1954-1955 (Box 4)
    - "Intermediate Boys" class, 1955 (Box 4)
    - "Bethany" class, 1956 (Box 4)
    - "Golden Circle" class, 1958 (Box 4)
  - Vacation Bible school records
    - 1953 (Box 4)
    - 1955 (Box 4)
    - 1957 (Box 4)
  - Photographs of church buildings and members, church activities, classes, groundbreaking service (Box 4)
- Earlier Records, ca. 1895-1978
  - Materials collected in 1941 for a history of the congregation (Reel 1)
  - Clippings concerning church activities and members (Reel 1)
  - State convention programs and materials (Reel 1)
  - Pastoral resignations (Reel 1)
  - Correspondence and general files, 1912-1933 (Reel 1)
  - Ministerial file of Rev. J. Allen Canby (Reel 1)
  - Correspondence and general files, 1934-1943 (Reel 1)
  - Ministerial file of Rev. E.C. Watterworth (Reel 1)
  - Correspondence and general files, 1944-1957 (Reel 1)
  - Correspondence and general files, 1958-1964 (Reel 2)
  - Materials for the Homecoming and Groundbreaking Day, 1962 (Reel 2)
  - Church legal papers: articles of association, by-laws, mortgage papers, etc. (Reel 2)
  - Materials for the history of other Michigan Disciples congregations (Reel 2)
  - Church board minutes
    - 1912-1915 (Reel 2)
    - 1915-1917 (Reel 2)
    - 1930-1949 (Reel 2)
  - Newsletter: The Church Messenger, 1947-1958 (Reel 2)
    (some issues missing)